Guide to the Elithe Hamilton Kirkland Papers
The Wittliff Collections
- Personal Papers, 1910-1991, undated
  - Correspondence, 1920-1991, undated
    - White, Owen P. (Collier's), 1931-1936 (Box 37, Box 1)
    - Williams, Alice, 1961 (Box 37, Box 2)
    - Wimberley, Texas (including correspondence with Nancie Austin and Donna Campbell), 1979-1984 (Box 37, Box 3)
    - Writers Round-Up, 1959 (Box 37, Box 4)
    - X-Y-Z, 1961 (Box 37, Box 5)
    - Unidentified (correspondents with first names only), 1934-1991 (Box 37, Box 6)
  - J. Frank Dobie Material, 1927-1976, undated
    - J. Frank Dobie correspondence, 1944-1963 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Martha Dobie correspondence, 1959-1976 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence (regarding J. Frank Dobie), 1946-1976 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Notes and correspondence regarding Southwestern University's Dobie Day celebrations, 1952 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Articles written by Dobie (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Articles written about Dobie (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Unpublished Writing
      - "This I Believe" statement (Box 38, Folder 7)
      - Incomplete Guide to Books on Texas and the Southwest, 1938 (Box 38, Folder 8)
      - English exam, University of Texas, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 9)
      - Unidentified radio script regarding Longhorns (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Photographs of Dobie (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - Photoprints of drawings for Dobie's The Mustangs (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - Books by J. Frank Dobie, 1929-1952
      - Apache Gold and Yaqui Silver. Little, Brown, and Co.: Boston, 1950 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Coronado's Children: Lost Mines and Buried Treasures of the Southwest. Grosset & Dunlap: New York, 1930 (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - The Flavor of Texas. Dealey and Lowe: Dallas. (inscribed to Elithe Beal), 1936 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      - Guide to Life and Literature of the Southwest. University Press in Dallas, Southern Methodist University: Dallas, 1943 (Box 39, Folder 4)
      - John C. Duval: First Texas Man of Letters. Southwest Review: Dallas. (inscribed to Elithe Beal), 1939 (Box 40, Folder 1)
      - The Longhorns. Little, Brown and Co.: Boston. (inscribed to Elithe Beal), 1941 (Box 40, Folder 2)
      - The Mexico I Like. University Press in Dallas, Southern Methodist University: Dallas. (originally published as Tongues of the Monte), 1942 (Box 40, Folder 3)
      - The Mustangs. Little, Brown, and Co.: Boston, 1952 (Box 41, Folder 1)
      - The Mustangs. Little, Brown, and Co.: Boston. 1st edition. Inscribed to Eva Hamilton., 1952 (Box 41, Folder 2)
      - On the Open Range. Banks Upshaw and Company: Dallas. (inscribed to Elithe Beal), 1940 (Box 41, Folder 3)
      - A Texan in England. Little, Brown and Co.: Boston, 1945 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - A Vaquero of the Brush Country. Grosset & Dunlap: New York, 1929 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Publications edited for the Texas Folklore Society, 1927-1961
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Coffee in the Gourd. Texas Folklore Society: Austin. (Reprint of 1923 edition), 1935 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      - Boatright, Mody C., Dobie, J. Frank, and Ransom, Harry H., eds. Coyote Wisdom. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1938 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Foller De Drinkin' Gou'd. Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, Vol. VII. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1928 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Man, Bird, and Beast. Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, Vol. VIII. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1930 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      - Boatright, Mody C., Dobie, J. Frank, and Ransom, Harry H., eds. Mustangs and Cow Horses. Publication of the Texas Folklore Society, Vol. XVI. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1940 (Box 43, Folder 3)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Puro Mexicano. Texas Folklore Society Publications Number XII. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1935 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      - Boatright, Mody C., Dobie, J. Frank, and Ransom, Harry H., eds. In the Shadow of History. Texas Folklore Society Publications Number XV. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1939 (Box 44, Folder 1)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Southwestern Lore. Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, Number IX. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1931 (Box 44, Folder 2)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Spur of the Cock. Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, Number XI. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1933 (Box 44, Folder 3)
      - Dobie, J. Frank. Storytellers I Have Known. Texas Folklore Society: Dallas, 1961 (Box 44, Folder 4)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed., and Boatright assoc. ed. Straight Texas. Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, Number XIII. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1937 (Box 44, Folder 5)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Texas and Southwestern Lore. Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, Number VI. Texas Folk-lore Society: Austin, 1927 (Box 44, Folder 6)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Tone the Bell Easy. Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, Number X. Texas Folklore Society: Austin, 1932 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Additional Dobie Publications, 1947-1963, undated
      - As the Moving Finger Writ, Christmas 1955 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - Books and Christmas, Christmas 1950 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - A Christmas Remembrance, Christmas 1951 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - E. Douglas Branch, Singularisimo. Reprint from Southwest Review, Vol. XLVII, Number 2, Spring 1962 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - His Looks and My Ways Would Hang Any Man, Christmas 1956 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - Hunting Cousin Sally, Christmas 1961 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - James Bowie, Big Dealer, Christmas 1957 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - The Mezcla Man. El Paso Del Norte, 1954 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - My Salute to Gene Rhodes, Christmas 1947 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - A Plot of Earth, Christmas 1953 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - A Schoolteacher in Alpine, Christmas 1962 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - Tom Gilroy's Fiddler, Christmas 1958 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - The Writer and His Region, undated (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Additonal Dobie Collaborations, 1931-1969
      - Dobie, J. Frank. The Seven Mustangs, and Goddard, Ruth. Ralph Ogden. Jenkins Publishing Company: Austin & New York. (inscribed by Ruth Goddard to Elithe Hamilton Kirkland.), 1969 (Box 45, Folder 3)
      - Rogers, John William. Finding Literature on The Texas Plains, with a Representative Bibliography of Books on the Southwest by J. Frank Dobie. The Southwest Press: Dallas, 1931 (Box 45, Folder 4)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. E342: A Collection of Stray Mavericks Caught, Roped, and Branded by Members of the "Big Corral" (English 342: Life and Literature of the Southwest). No. 1. University of Texas: Austin, 1940 (Box 45, Folder 5)
      - Dobie, J. Frank, ed. Typically Texian: Being a Collection of Dog-Run Sayings and Doings by the Lazy Easers of English 342 (Life and Literature of the Southwest). No. III. University of Texas: Austin, 1942 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Notes, undated
    - Dream notes (Box 45, Folder 7-8)
    - General notes (Box 45, Folder 9, Box 46, Box 47)
  - Photographic Material, circa 1910-1991
    - 1910-1919 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - 1920-1929 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - 1931 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - 1930-1935 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 48, Folder 5-6)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 48, Folder 8-9)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - 1990-1999 (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - Family and friends, undated (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Negatives (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - Postcards (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - Halftone portraits and paper cover (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Framed photographs (Box 49, Folder 5-7)
  - Speeches, circa 1940-1991, undated
    - "Speechmaking on journalism" (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - "Speaking engagements: Correspondence and notes - good ideas for future use", 1952-1960 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - American Association of University of Women, 1960 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Coleman Library Program, 1986 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution, 1987 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Texas Joint Council of Teachers of English, 1983 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Texas Sesquicentennial - Clippings (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Texas Sesquicentennial - Printed materials (Box 50, Folder 8-9, Box 51, Folder 1-2)
    - Texas Voices (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Subjects, 1936-1991, undated
    - Colt Revolver (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Council Grove Conference, 1984 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Council Grove Conference, 1988 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Fath, Conrad (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Fort Worth Fiesta, 1936 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Ghosts and voodoo (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Hamilton, Free (eulogy) (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Hanging Tree and Marble Falls Spirit (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Harmonic Convergence (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Huntsville, TX (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Jefferson, TX (Marsha Thomas program) (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - MacLaine, Shirley (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - MENSA (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - Mineral Wells (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Nashville visit, 1947 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - North Texas State Teachers College (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Numerology (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Rush, Virginia (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Saltillo Description by Blanca Blasquez (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Smithsonian Lectures (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - Spielberg, Steven (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - Spiritual Frontiers Fellowship (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - Texas Institute of Letters (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - Texas Society for Mental Hygiene (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - Tinney, Kim (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - Travis, Edmunds (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Whitman, Walt (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Wimberley (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - Yogananda (Box 53, Folder 16)
  - Artifacts and Oversized, 1940-1952, undated
    - Rocks (2); Carved beavers (2) (Box 54)
    - Texas shaped serving bowl; Horseshoes (2) (Box 55)
    - Texas Women's Hall of Fame Plaque (Box 56)
    - Typewriter (Box 57)
    - Plastic typewriter cover (Box 58)
    - Pressed flowers (Box 59)
    - Copy of autobiographical sketch of Peck Woodside, 1940 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Draft of "Heather, For Luck" (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - "The Disappearance of Widow Ellen" partial draft of stage treatment (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Divine Average draft of screen treatment (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - "The Disappearance of Widow Ellen" draft of screenplay (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - Award to Kirkland from Theta Sigma Phi at 11th Annual Writers' Roundup, 1959 (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - 1 matted 8x10 photo of Kirkland receiving Texas Women's Hall of Fame Award, mat signed by Governor Clements; 1 matted 8x10 photo of 1987 recipients of Texas Women's Hall of Fame Award, 1987, undated (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - Dobie Day research – photocopies of correspondence and notes, 1952 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - 1 11x14 photo of Kirkland used in April 1990 Texas Monthly article (Box 61, Folder 2)
    - 1 11x14 photo of flute player in "Hear the Flute" (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - 1 cover photo for "The Disappearance of Widow Ellen" (11x14 mounted on mat) (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - 1 annotated map of Tabasco, Mexico; 1 annotated map of Tabasco, Mexico printed for CIA. Aeronautica del Sur S.A. (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Signed copies of Jenny Lind Porter's poem "Wedded Souls", undated (Box 61, Folder 6)